<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="Concepts">
    <title>Concepts</title>
    <para> Use the Cloud Networks API v2.0 to manage the following entities: </para>
    <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
            <term>Network</term>
            <listitem>
                <para>An isolated virtual Layer 2 domain. A network can also be a virtual, or logical, switch. See <olink
                        targetdoc="cn-devguide" targetptr="conceptNetwork">“Network”</olink>.</para>
            </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
            <term>Subnet</term>
            <listitem>
                <para>An IPv4 or IPv6 address block from which IP addresses that are assigned to servers on a specified
                    network are selected. See <olink targetdoc="cn-devguide" targetptr="conceptSubnet"
                    >“Subnet”</olink>.</para>
            </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
            <term>Ports</term>
            <listitem>
                <para>A virtual, or logical, switch port on a specified network. See <olink targetdoc="cn-devguide"
                        targetptr="conceptPort">“Port”</olink>.</para>
            </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
            <term>Router</term>
            <listitem>
                <para>A router is used with a layer-3 extension to interconnect subnets and forward traffic among them. See
                        <olink targetdoc="cn-devguide" targetptr="conceptRouter">“Router”</olink>.</para>
            </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <para>These entities have autogenerated unique identifiers and support basic create, read, update, and delete (CRUD)
        functions with the <code>POST</code>, <code>GET</code>, <code>PUT</code>, and <code>DELETE</code> methods.</para>

    <!-- Network -->
    <section xml:id="conceptNetwork">
        <title>Network</title>
        <para>A network is an isolated virtual Layer 2 broadcast domain that is typically reserved for the tenant who created
            it, unless the tenant configures the network to be shared. Tenants can create multiple networks until they reach
            the thresholds per-tenant quota.</para>
        <para>In the Cloud Networks API v2.0, the network is the main entity. Ports and subnets are always associated with a
            network.</para>
        <para>The following table describes the attributes for network objects.</para>
        <table rules="all" width="100%">
            <caption>Network Attributes</caption>
            <col width="20%"/>
            <col width="15%"/>
            <col width="70%"/>
            <thead>
                <tr>
                    <th>Attribute</th>
                    <th>Type</th>
                    <th>Description</th>
                </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
                <tr>
                    <td>id</td>
                    <td>uuid-str</td>
                    <td>The UUID for the network.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>name</td>
                    <td>String</td>
                    <td>The human-readable name for the network. The name might not be unique.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>admin_state_up</td>
                    <td>Bool</td>
                    <td>The administrative state of network (<code>True</code> or <code>False</code>). If the network is down
                            (<code>False</code>), the network does not forward packets.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>status</td>
                    <td>String</td>
                    <td>The status of network operation (<code>ACTIVE</code>, <code>DOWN</code>, <code>BUILD</code>, or
                            <code>ERROR</code>).</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>subnets</td>
                    <td>list(uuid-str)</td>
                    <td>Lists the subnets associated with this network.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>shared</td>
                    <td>Bool</td>
                    <td>Specifies whether the network resource can be accessed by any tenant (<code>True</code> or
                            <code>False</code>).</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>tenant_id</td>
                    <td>uuid-str</td>
                    <td>The owner of the network. Only admin users can specify a tenant_id other than their own.</td>
                </tr>
            </tbody>
        </table>
    </section>

    <!-- Subnet -->
    <section xml:id="conceptSubnet">
        <title>Subnet</title>
        <para>A subnet represents an IP address block that can be used to assign IP addresses to virtual instances. Each
            subnet must have a CIDR and must be associated with a network. IP addresses can be selected either from the whole
            subnet CIDR or from allocation pools that are specified by the user.</para>
        <para>A subnet can also optionally have a gateway, a list of DNS name servers, and host routes. This information is
            pushed to instances whose interfaces are associated with the subnet.</para>
        <para>The following table describes the attributes for subnet objects.</para>
        <table rules="all" width="100%">
            <caption>Subnet Attributes</caption>
            <col width="20%"/>
            <col width="15%"/>
            <col width="70%"/>
            <thead>
                <tr>
                    <th>Attribute</th>
                    <th>Type</th>
                    <th>Description</th>
                </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
                <tr>
                    <td>id</td>
                    <td>uuid-str</td>
                    <td>The UUID that represents the subnet.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>network_id</td>
                    <td>uuid-str</td>
                    <td>The UUID for the network.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>name</td>
                    <td>String</td>
                    <td>The human-readable name for the subnet. The name might not be unique.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>ip_version</td>
                    <td>Int</td>
                    <td>The IP version (4 or 6).</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>cidr</td>
                    <td>String</td>
                    <td>The CIDR that represents the IP address range for this subnet, based on the IP version. A valid CIDR
                        takes the form <emphasis role="italics">networkAddress</emphasis>/<emphasis role="italics"
                            >prefix</emphasis> (for example, 192.168.3.0/24).</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>gateway_ip</td>
                    <td>String</td>
                    <td>The default gateway used by devices in this subnet (valid IP address or <code>null</code>).</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>dns_nameservers</td>
                    <td>list(str)</td>
                    <td>Lists the DNS name servers used by hosts in this subnet.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>allocation_pools</td>
                    <td>list(dict)</td>
                    <td>Lists the subranges of CIDR that are available for dynamic allocation to ports [ { "start":
                        "10.0.0.2", "end": "10.0.0.254"} ].</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>host_routes</td>
                    <td>list(dict)</td>
                    <td>The routes that should be used by devices with IP addresses from this subnet (not including the local
                        subnet route).</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>enable_dhcp</td>
                    <td>Bool</td>
                    <td>Specifies whether DHCP is enabled for this subnet (<code>True</code> or <code>False</code>).</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>tenant_id</td>
                    <td>uuid-str</td>
                    <td>The owner of network. Only admin users can specify a tenant_id other than their own.</td>
                </tr>
            </tbody>
        </table>
    </section>

    <!-- Port -->
    <section xml:id="conceptPort">
        <title>Port</title>
        <para>A port represents a virtual switch port on a logical network switch. Virtual instances attach their interfaces
            to ports. The logical port also defines the MAC address and the IP address or addresses to be assigned to the
            interfaces plugged into them. When IP addresses are associated with a port, this also implies that the port is
            associated with a subnet, as the IP address was taken from the allocation pool for a specific subnet.</para>
        <para>The following table describes the attributes for port objects.</para>
        <table rules="all" width="100%">
            <caption>Port Attributes</caption>
            <col width="20%"/>
            <col width="15%"/>
            <col width="70%"/>
            <thead>
                <tr>
                    <th>Attribute</th>
                    <th>Type</th>
                    <th>Description</th>
                </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
                <tr>
                    <td>id</td>
                    <td>uuid-str</td>
                    <td>The UUID for the port.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>network_id</td>
                    <td>uuid-str</td>
                    <td>The UUID for the network associated with this port.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>name</td>
                    <td>String</td>
                    <td>The human-readable name for the port. The name might not be unique.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>admin_state_up</td>
                    <td>Bool</td>
                    <td>The administrative state of the port (<code>True</code> or <code>False</code>). If the network is
                        down (<code>False</code>), the network does not forward packets.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>status</td>
                    <td>String</td>
                    <td>The status of network operation (<code>ACTIVE</code>, <code>DOWN</code>, <code>BUILD</code>, or
                            <code>ERROR</code>).</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>mac_address</td>
                    <td>String</td>
                    <td>The MAC address for this port.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>fixed_ips</td>
                    <td>list(dict)</td>
                    <td>Specifies IP addresses for the port, thus associating the port itself with the subnets from
                        which the IP addresses are picked.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>device_id</td>
                    <td>String</td>
                    <td>Identifies the device (for example, virtual server) using this port.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>device_owner</td>
                    <td>String</td>
                    <td>Identifies the entity (for example, DHCP agent) using this port.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>tenant_id</td>
                    <td>uuid-str</td>
                    <td>The owner of the network. Only admin users can specify a tenant_id other than their own.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>security_groups</td>
                    <td>list(dict)</td>
                    <td>Specifies the IDs of any security groups associated with a port.</td>
                </tr>
            </tbody>
        </table>
    </section>

    <!-- Layer 3 Router -->
    <section xml:id="conceptRouter">
        <title>Router</title>
        <para> A router is used to interconnect subnets and forward traffic among them. Another feature of the router is to
            NAT internal traffic to external networks. A router has an interface for each associated subnet. By default, the
            IP address of an interface is the subnet's gateway IP. Also, whenever a router is associated with a subnet, a
            port for that router interface will be added to the subnet's network. See <olink targetdoc="cn-devguide"
                targetptr="api_ext_layer3_router">“Extension - Layer 3 Networking (Router)”</olink> for the associated API
            operations.</para>
        <para>The following table describes the attributes for router objects.</para>
        <table rules="all" width="100%">
            <caption>Router Attributes</caption>
            <col width="20%"/>
            <col width="15%"/>
            <col width="70%"/>
            <thead>
                <tr>
                    <th>Attribute</th>
                    <th>Type</th>
                    <th>Description</th>
                </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
                <tr>
                    <td>id</td>
                    <td>uuid-str</td>
                    <td>The unique identifier for the router.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>name</td>
                    <td>String</td>
                    <td>The human-readable name for the router. The name might not be unique.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>admin_state_up</td>
                    <td>Bool</td>
                    <td>The administrative state of router (<code>True</code> - router is up or
                            <code>False</code> - router is down).</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>status</td>
                    <td>String</td>
                    <td>Indicates whether a router is currently operational or not..</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>tenant_id</td>
                    <td>uuid-str</td>
                    <td>The owner of router. Only admin users can specify a tenant_id other than their own.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>external_gateway_info</td>
                    <td>dict</td>
                    <td>Information about the external gateway for the router.</td>
                </tr>
            </tbody>
        </table>
    </section>

    <!-- Glossary -->
    <glossary role="auto"/>
</chapter>
